# Samuel Chávez

Guatemala City, GTM 01016 | +502.311.73211 | <a href="mailto:schavezfuentes@gmail.com">schavezfuentes@gmail.com</a> | <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/samuelchavez/">https://github.com/samuelchavez/</a> | <a href="https://github.com/samuelchavez/">https://github.com/samuelchavez/</a> |

# **Software Engineer**

Innovative and analytical Technical Professional with 10 years of experience in software architecture, programming, and debugging, troubleshooting, team management and development, and streamlining software delivery and testing within fast-paced and critical technological environments

Software Prototyping & Development
Project Management
Programming & Coding
Strategic Planning & Problem Solving
Customer Service & User Satisfaction
Attention to Detail
Leadership & Cross-Functional Collaborations
Multitasking & Prioritisation
Oral & Written Communication
Web Prototyping

Supervised cross-functional teams and employed concepts, practices, resources, and procedures to drive the design, development, and architecture of software.

Mentored various junior staff and promoted company advancement through continuous research, development, and technological training.

Formulated and managed specifications, workflow, and documentation for the modification of complex software programming applications

Communicative and personable; able to lead teams, learn and develop new software, tools, and techniques, and utilize complex technologies to implement, execute, and solve user issues. Extremely organized, able to multitask, manage time, and convey results via technical reports.

# CAREER ACCOMPLISHMENTS

Within the last nine years, successfully programmed, led, and launched more than 10 widely used applications in Guatemala.

Effectively defined best practices in addition to directing and executing all standard, technological processes which led to a 50% decrease in companywide production time.

Utilized skills and experiences to promote and achieve company growth from 0 users to +30,000.

Garnered \$100K and the company's first 20 clients after launch.

Successfully transformed a software architecture from a uniformed, rigid approach to a modularized approach.

### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

EDOO S.A. | Guatemala City, GTM

1/2015 - Present

#### **CHIEF TECHNOLOGY OFFICER**

Develop company technical aspects and strategies to ensure alignment with company goals and objectives. Research and implement new technologies that yield competitive advantages, manage platform configuration processes, and implement new and existing system infrastructures to guarantee consistent functionality and efficiency. Monitor IT budget and operations as well as developed and programmed all core production applications (200K LoC) to guarantee adherence to quality and coding standards. Hire, train, and mentor new programmers, regulate numerous technical projects, and developed internal support libraries (10K LoC).

## **Key Contributions & Achievements:**

- Serve as a Co-Founder; responsible for spearheading all aspects of technical development in addition to ensuring organizational enhancement which resulted in a growth from zero to more than thirty thousand paying users.
- Act as a Consultant; in charge of training and advising EDOO's clients on various aspects of technical skills such as planning technological curricula and employing techniques to ensure better use of cloud tools by schools.
- Employed direct sales methodologies and led company fundraising strategies to raise \$100K USD from a local investor which resulted in the acquisition of the first 20 customers (schools).
- Reduced production time by 50% after implementing standard processes for all technology roles.

# Samuel Chávez

# Page 2 • Career Progression (Cont.)

- Facilitated the construction of a powerful and comprehensive educational management suite for Latin American private schools.
- Efficiently recruited and coached 10 programmers which boosted coding throughput by 20.

#### Universidad Francisco Marroquín | Universidad Del Valle De Guatemala | Guatemala City, GTM

1/2013 - Present

#### **TENURED PROFESSOR**

Educate undergraduate students on the fundamentals of Object-Oriented Programming, Python Programming, Modelling and Simulation, Web Systems and Technologies, Artificial Intelligence, as well as Elements of Machine Learning. Conduct class and student evaluations, by way of quizzes and exams, and offer individual tutoring and mentorship to students when needed. Develop and distribute educational content and employ learner centred and activity-based methodologies to ensure optimal student engagement.

#### **Key Contributions & Achievements:**

- Consistently achieve one of the highest grades, as a result of student feedback, within the Computer Science Department.
- Launched an open-source project for 1v1 board games playing, specifically designed to run AI-based tournaments.

#### PideloRapido S.A | Nozzmo | Guatemala City, GTM

10/2010 - 11/2016

#### SOFTWARE DEVELOPER/CHIEF TECHNOLOGY OFFICER

Researched, designed, implemented, and managed applications for several companies with the aim of providing top level service to all end users. Utilized user-centric design approaches and integrated software components to develop web and mobile applications, verify and deploy systems, and update the company's technological stack. Gathered and evaluated user feedback, identified areas that needed updates, troubleshot and debugged existing software, as well as determined operational practicality of all existing software.

#### **Key Contributions & Achievements:**

- Performed as a Liaison; interfaced with clients to ensure the accurate acquisition of required information during component shipments.
- Successfully led PideloRapido's software refactor from a monolithic approach to a microservices architecture.
- Efficiently designed a high performance and scalable architecture that processed hundreds of daily orders.

## **TECHNICAL PROFICIENCIES**

Languages and similar: Python; ES6+; JavaScript; Java; Kotlin; HTML5; CSS3; PHP;

Frameworks / Other: React / React Native; Redux; Gatsby; Django; NumPy; Pandas; TensorFlow; WordPress; SaaS;

### **EDUCATION AND CERTIFICATIONS**

Universidad Del Valle De Guatemala | Guatemala City, GTM Bachelor of Science, Computer Science (Summa Cum Laude) (GPA: 3.84 or 96%) (2011)

## **Awards & Honours**

Won the National Champion of Physics title at the XIX Guatemalan Science Olympiad (best in the country)

Acquired Honorific Mention in Mathematics at the XIX Guatemalan Science Olympiad (top four in the country)

Received the Juan Bautista Gutiérrez Scholarship (they gave 10 scholarships in the country)

#### Certifications

Machine Learning (Coursera) - 2019